In the last video, we talked about how
to gather input. Now that we're
gathering input, we may not always know
what we've put into our variables
because that input could be coming from
anywhere. So, if we don't know what's in
our variable, we might not know what
type of information it's storing. So,
for example, first name right now is
storing a string. Um, but we also
mentioned that there are other types of
variables. So, we could say I'm going to
call this variable my var. Um, and if I
type the keyword true, then it would be
holding a boolean. If I type the number
eight, then it's holding an integer. If
I type 8.8, now it's holding a float.
So, we talked about many different types
of variables. So, how do we know what's
being stored in a variable that's coming
from outside input? Um,
one of the ways we can do this is using
the keyword type of.
So, we are gathering username. So, if we
want to know the type of username, we'd
say type of username.
Right now, what I've typed won't do
anything. it'll determine the type of
username and then it won't do anything
with it. If we want to show that
information, then we need to use one of
the output um methods that I showed you
prior. So, we could say let's alert the
type of username. So, it's going to take
the username, figure out what type of
variable it is, and then alert it. So,
if we save this and we come over here,
says, and I'm going to reload the page.
So we'll reload the page and it says
what is your username and we'll say I am
Batman
and it says the type of information
there is a string. So the information we
got back from the user is a string. So
let's close that. And now we'll come
over to Visual Studio Code. Um let's
create another variable here. We'll call
this say let my name equal or sorry let
equal true. And we're going to say,
let's see what type of variable happy
is. So I've created a new variable. It's
called happy. It's a boolean. And so
when I show this alert message, I should
see a boolean. Because we're not using
username right now, I'm going to comment
it out. You could put two slashes in
front of it. Or you could just click
into the line that you want commented
and hit command slash or control slash
if you're on Windows and save that. Now
if we come back over here, it pops up a
message and says this is a boolean. Um
if we change this variable to age and we
put it as eight and we say what is the
type of age?
If we come back over here, we can see
the age is a number. Well, fantastic.
This type of is showing us what is being
stored in a variable. So let's go back
and let's see what's in username. So,
we're going to save our code, come back
over, and for our username, we're going
to enter the number eight and hit okay.
Interesting. It said that the number
eight is a string.
And that is correct. Anytime you gather
information using the prompt input, it
returns it as a string. So, this prompt
input says, "What is your username?"
They enter the information and it is the
equivalent of typing in quotes 8 and
this is a string. Remember to be an
integer it needs to not have the quotes.
Everything that comes back from a prompt
is a string. Sometimes we need to work
with it like it's a number like age. And
so in order to do that we need to
convert which will be the topic of our
next video. In summary for this video
you use the keyword type of to figure
out what type of variable you have when
you don't know. And that concludes this
video.